Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project Collection AD.RG.023
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project Collection
2019 - Ongoing
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.RG.023
2 Terabytes 1100 items
122 oral_history_interviews 122 oral history interviews recorded as audio and/or video sessions.
The NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project is an ongoing archival oral history project that seeks to record the history of NYU Abu Dhabi and the historical memories, experiences, and knowledge of members of the NYU Abu Dhabi community. The collection includes both video and audio recorded oral history interviews, conducted both in-person and remotely from 2019-Present.
Scope and Contents
The NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project is an ongoing archival oral history project that seeks to record the history of NYU Abu Dhabi and the historical memories, experiences, and knowledge of members of the NYU Abu Dhabi community. The collection includes both video and audio recorded oral history interviews, conducted both in-person and remotely from 2019-Present. Drawing on the concept of storytelling in knowledge management, the NYUAD Archivist regularly conducts with individuals and groups as a way to enhance understanding about NYUAD's people, spaces, culture, research, programs, and community traditions.
Anyone interested in understanding the NYU Abu Dhabi community -- its people, its spaces, its culture, community traditions -- will find this body of interviews valuable. The coming together of recording stories is also a meaningful activity on its own, leading to the archiving of group origin stories that will be preserved for future generations. Stories of migration to and from Abu Dhabi and the UAE, as well as impressions of the region, are also discussed.
Interviews conducted have been summarized, and some have edited transcripts. As the project is continuously ongoing and iteratively processed, users may inquire about available transcripts.
Biographical / Historical
The project began as an oral history storytelling effort to commemorate the University's 10th Anniversary, and was branded the "NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project" in September 2019. In October 2019, the project launched a pilot effort during the University's first Alumni Weekend, which welcomed back the Class of 2014. Attendees were invited to volunteer for a 30-minute interview session with interviewers from the Archives asking questions such as first impressions of Abu Dhabi, memories of the Downtown Campus (DTC) and Sama Tower days. Alumni, faculty, and staff participated.
Since 2019, the project has evolved into one of the primary methods for acquiring knowledge about the NYU Abu Dhabi campus for the University Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Some interviews in this collection have been temporarily restricted, and will not appear in this guide until they are open for access and research. Restriction periods have been collaboratively determined by the interviewees and the NYUAD Archivist, and exist for a variety of reasons.
Access to open interviews will be provided onsite in the Archives and Special Collection Reading Room of the NYUAD Library. On a case by case basis, remote access may be arranged.
Curated excerpts from the NYUAD Memory Project are available for listening via the "NYUAD Map of Micromemories" online StoryMap, a mobile-friendly, "spatial listening experience" created by the University Archives team in the NYUAD Library:
https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/f58cb30a899448738783e8f645e9616c
Future plans for access include providing browsable access via the Library's NYU authenticated access site, hosted on the Preservica platform.
Related Materials
The NYUAD University Archives also includes other oral history collections, including the "From Downtown Campus to Saadiyat Island: Interviews with Early NYUAD Members" collection, and copies of "The Origin Story: An Oral History of NYU Abu Dhabi, 2005-2010."
- Alumni Weekend Pilot Project, October 2019
  Scope and Contents
  This series of in-person interviews were conducted in conjunction with the Class of 2014 (and NYU Abu Dhabi's first) five-year reunion, as a pilot project ahead of the NYU Abu Dhabi 10th anniversary. Answering a call for participation, interviewees in seven sessions signed up to record their memories on Friday, October 10, 2019, in between reunion activities. These short form sessions were guided by a set of general prompts and questions that archivists Brad Bauer or Lauren Kata asked, while digital media specialist Rebecca Pittam recorded. The sessions took place in "The Living Room," a quiet space facilitated by the Campus Life (Student Affairs) that the Memory Project team booked specifically for the recordings.
  - Interview session with Goffredo Puccetti and Brad Bauer (29:23), 09 Oct 2019; ADRG023_001; 29 minutes; 42.75 Gigabytes (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_001)
    Video-recorded session with Goffredo Puccetti, Assistant Professor of Practice of Visual Arts, recorded on October 9, 2019, and interviewed by Brad Bauer, Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the NYUAD Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Goffredo talks about his professional and personal journey which led him to NYU Abu Dhabi. He showcases the new NYUAD Bulletin which has been redesigned to reflect the growth of the university, as well as to incorporate the arabic script of 'NYU Abu Dhabi', a project he worked on with his students. He also mentions his role as a Faculty Fellow in Residence, which allowed himself, alongside his wife, to cultivate new traditions like tiramisu and taboo nights with the students. The switch from design practice to academia has been an interesting one, but Goffredo has realised the impact of teaching on students' lives, as well as settled into his design role on campus, thinking about things such as designing for accessibility on campus.
    Puccetti, Goffredo
  - Interview Session with Dana Downey and Lauren Kata (33:36), 10 Oct 2019; ADRG023_002 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_002)
    Video-recorded session with Dana Downey, recorded on Thursday October 10th 2019 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian in Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Dana Downey reflects on her journey working for the Career Development Center (CDC) at NYUAD in 2014 as the university was preparing for its first graduating class, until now, working at the Saadiyat campus. She describes her initial attraction to the region and the university, and the benefits of its diverse population to her life and the lives of her family. Dana recounts the realities of the low staff-student ratio which meant that there was a lot of contact between staff and students which was both advantageous and disadvantageous. She also touches on the trials in creating some of the CDC's first student campaigns which relied heavily on student feedback and engagement.
  - Interview Session with Wayne Young and Brad Bauer (31:52), 09 Oct 2019; ADRG023_003 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_003)
    Video-recorded session with Wayne Young, Director of Wellness at NYUAD, recorded on Wednesday, October 9th, 2019, and facilitated by Brad Bauer, Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    In this interview, Wayne Young reflects on the process and stories behind the designing of the Athletics and Wellness program at NYUAD. He talks about the challenges, such as the climate of Abu Dhabi and the lack of facilities in the earlier years of NYUAD, and about creative solutions like renting facilities at Al Muna Academy and the Armed Forces Officers Club. He shares stories about his experience of navigating the new cultural environment, traveling with students for sports events (e.g. Dead2Red relay race in Jordan), and designing and introducing the NYUAD mascot -- Faiza The Falcon.
  - Interview session with Leah (Reynolds) Ritter, Manuel Nivia, Emily (Eagan) Nivia, and Lauren Kata (44:00), 10 Oct 2019; ADRG023_004 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_004)
    Leah (Reynolds) Ritter, Emily (Eagan) Nivia, and Manuel Nivia, NYU Abu Dhabi Class of 2014 alumni, recorded on Thursday, October 10, 2019 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    In this session, Leah, Emily and Manuel each reflect on the early days of being a student at NYU Abu Dhabi, for example, arriving and settling into Sama Tower, why they each chose NYUAD, traditions they remember such as the 24 hour film race and Rain Day. They reflect on living in Abu Dhabi, studying abroad within the country and internationally, and enjoyable aspects of student life in Sama Tower and the Downtown Campus. They mention the challenges of adjustment to a new cultural context, as well as the pressure of a rigorous academic program.
  - Interview Session with Abishek Mehra and Brad Bauer (27:26), 10 Oct 2019; ADRG023_005 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_005)
    Video-recorded session with Abishek Mehra, Class of 2014 alumnus, recorded on October 10th 2019 and facilitated by Brad Bauer, Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the NYUAD Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Abishek talks about his experience at NYU Abu Dhabi from Candidate Weekend through life in downtown Abu Dhabi, New York study away and life after graduation. For Abishek, NYU Abu Dhabi was a new academic experience with its liberal arts education, a system with which Mehra was not familiar. He reminisces on his challenges in freshman year transitioning from an Indian system to an American system, and how he was able to overcome those challenges through close access to teaching assistants, professors and deans. He also discusses his time in New York which was completely different to Abu Dhabi in terms of academic culture, city culture and level of independence. Abishek is adamant that NYU Abu Dhabi's greatest lesson is that you can do anything you set your mind to.
  - Interview Session with Janos Kun and Lauren Kata (19:13), 10 Oct 2019; ADRG023_006 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_006)
    Video-recorded Memory Project session with Janos Kun, Class of 2014 alumnus recorded on Thursday, October 10, 2019, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    In this interview, Janos Kun reflects on his first memories of arriving in the UAE, his Marhaba week and his engagement with Abu Dhabi downtown, specifically about his favorite cafes and restaurants. He also discusses the role that NYUAD Athletics Department played in his personal growth by making sports a meaningful part of his self-care routine for many years. Janos Kun shares his impressions of the most memorable courses he took at NYU Abu Dhabi, such as Foundations of Science, Numerical Methods, Gardens of Eden, and Food in the Global City. He concludes by talking about his post-graduation experiences with his fellow schoolmates and the reunions they had all over the world.
  - Interview session with Hazel Raja, Jay Raja, and Brad Bauer (34:21), 10 Oct 2019; ADRG023_007 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_007)
    Video-recorded NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project session with Hazel Raja, Assistant Dean of Students and Director of the Career Development Center at NYU Abu Dhabi, and Jay Raja, Assistant Director of Fitness and Wellness Department, recorded on Thursday, October 10, 2019, and facilitated by Brad Bauer, Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    n this interview, Hazel and Jay Raja describe their first impressions of the NYUAD Downtown Campus, particularly the "trailer-like" outside and the impressive inside of the campus. They also recall a large number of construction sites around DTC. They share their initial amazement with life in Abu Dhabi (e.g. big apartment, pre-filled fridge), and the subsequent phase of homesickness and disappointment, which did not last long. Jay shares his story of starting a career in fitness at NYUAD, and Hazel describes her first days of working at the Career Center as daunting, but exciting at the same time. They describe the evolution of their respective departments over time. Hazel and Jay talk about their special places off-campus, such as Foodlands for shawarma, a park opposite to the Grand Mosque for sunset-watching, and Mushrif Park for walks with their daughter. In addition, they contrast their lives at DTC and the Saadiyat Campus and name their favorite campus community events including Cultural Nights, Pakistani Mock Wedding, and Community Cricket Match.
- Pre-Covid in-person interviews, February 2020
  - Interview session with Francesca Bizzarri, Goffredo Puccetti, and Lauren Kata (45:13), 18 Feb 2020; ADRG023_008 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_008)
    Video-recorded Memory Project session with Francesca Bizzarri, Artist in Residence and Goffredo Puccetti, Assistant Professor of Practice of Visual Arts, recorded on February 18, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Francesca and Goffredo recall their transition from living in Europe to their new lives at NYU Abu Dhabi. For the pair, it was not a difficult decision as they were both mobile with their careers. Language was a point of contention for Francesca who had only acted in French and Italian, and then had to move to an environment that was English and Arabic-based. They describe the move from the Downtown Campus where they would frequently hear the call to prayer, and labs were based in apartments, to the newer and more spacious Saadiyat campus. Becoming Faculty Fellows in Residence was integral to their experience at NYU Abu Dhabi. The FFIR model underwent adaptation from the NYU structure due to differences in goals and logistics, and the importance of FFIRs in supporting community discussions in grey areas. As FFIRs they became heavily involved with students and the community, cultivating traditions such as Tiramisu Night, Meet Greet and Eat, and Twirl It Like Luigi. They were also able to foster connections between students themselves, as well as between students and external guests such as Charlie Carmada and Alfio Quarteroni who visited the NYUAD Institute.
  - Interview session with Matteo Marciano and Lauren Kata (47:16), 18 Feb 2020; ADRG023_009 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_009)
    Video-recorded Memory Project session with Matteo Marciano, Assistant Program Head and Assistant Professor of Practice of Music Technology at NYU Abu Dhabi, recorded on Tuesday, February 18, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. The Memory Project is the NYUAD Library's contribution to celebrating the memories, experiences, traditions, stories and community history of NYU Abu Dhabi in commemoration of the University's 10th Anniversary. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    In this interview, Matteo Marciano reflects on his teaching experience on the NYU Abu Dhabi campus. He talks in great detail about his engagement with the NYUAD community through various initiatives, for example, the Faculty-Fellow-In-Residence program, Battle of the Bands, NYUAD recording studio, and regional seminar trips.
    This interview is a companion interview to the "Faculty Fellows In Residence" series and took place the same day as the group interview with Francesca Bizzarri, Goffredo Pucceti, and Adela Kovarova.
  - Interview session with Matteo Marciano, Adela Kovarova and Lauren Kata (19:25), 18 Feb 2020; ADRG023_010 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_010)
    Video-recorded Memory Project session with Adela Kovarova, Center Coordinator at the Center for Interacting Urban Networks and Matteo Marciano Assistant Program Head and Assistant Professor of Practice of Music Technology, recorded on February 18, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Adela and Matteo address their lives on campus in their professional realms as well as their roles as Faculty Fellows in Residence (FFIR). Adela describes the challenging transition moving from New York City to Abu Dhabi, avidly searching for employment and having to adapt to living on campus. As FFIRs, Matteo and Adela host community gatherings on campus in their dormitory apartment and off campus where attendees can interact with the local and other cultures, as well as promote and support the events of many other offices. They describe the process of learning to call Abu Dhabi home, which was made easier by the strong community presence living on campus and their cultivation of supportive relationships with their colleagues.
  - Interview session with Francesca Bizzarri, Goffredo Puccetti, Matteo Marciano, Adela Kovarova and Lauren Kata (51:51), 18 Feb 2020; ADRG023_011 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_011)
    Video-recorded session with Francesca Bizzarri, Artist in Residence, Goffredo Puccetti, Assistant Professor of Practice of Visual Arts, Adela Kovarova, Center Coordinator at the Center for Interacting Urban Networks and Matteo Marciano Assistant Program Head and Assistant Professor of Practice of Music Technology. Interview recorded on February 18 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    These four colleagues and friends reflect on their journeys at NYU Abu Dhabi, mainly through the Faculty Fellow in Residence (FFIR) Program, which Goffredo And Francesca introduced to Matteo and Adela. They talk about how the role has been mutually beneficial -- helping them forge connections with the student body, and helping ground students in traditions like Tiramisu Night and other programming. The four talk about setting boundaries while living in student dorms, the budget and logistical constraints of programming, and the biggest challenge of improving communication between them and other faculty members about their role. Food is a central theme as they talk about the endless possibilities of tiramisu creation, as well as cooking and ordering-in events that facilitated bonding.
  - Interview Session with Francesca Bizzarri, Aysan Celik and Lauren Kata (01:09:27), 26 February 2020; ADRG023_012; 15.97 Gigabytes (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_012)
    Video-recorded session with Aysan Celik, Faculty in the NYU Abu Dhabi Theater Program, and Artist in Residence Francesca Bizzarri, recorded on 26 February, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of either Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    Aysan and Francesca speak about the origins of their relationship at NYUAD, and the development of Theater and the Performing Arts at the University and in wider Abu Dhabi. Aysan reflects on teaching the Core Course 'Laughter,' which includes workshops on clowning taught by Francesca, where the pair teach students from various academic and cultural backgrounds to expand their knowledge and comfort levels. They touch on the differences between the Downtown Campus and the Saadiyat Campus -- the former allowing greater exposure to Abu Dhabi and connections to its residents, which is hard to recreate in the 'Saadiyat bubble'. They both reflect on their experiences at the University including the importance of language and accents, as well as working as a start-up in order to launch the Theater Program.
- Interviews with NYUAD Community Members [during Covid], Spring 2020 - Summer 2022
  Remote interviewing using Zoom began in April 2020, prompted by Covid-19 physical distancing restrictions. Interviewing using Zoom continued after the easing of restrictions, due to its numerous identified advantages.
  For more discussion on Zoom for oral history interviews, see archivist Lauren Kata's review of the technology:
  https://reviews.americanarchivist.org/2021/03/19/zoom-for-oral-history-projects/
  This series of interviews includes recordings conducted between April 2020 and August 2022. See later series for ongoing Memory Project interviews.
  - Interview session with Bill Bragin, Linsey Bostwick (Arts Center), and Lauren Kata (01:09:27), 16 Apr 2020; ADRG023_013 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_013)
    Video-recorded session with Executive Artistic Director Bill Bragin and Director of Artistic Planning, Linsey Bostwick, of the NYU Abu Dhabi Arts Center. The session was recorded via Zoom on April 16, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the NYUAD Library's Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.
    In this interview, Bragin and Bostwick discuss the origins of the NYU Abu Dhabi Arts Center, their role in growing the program, and the particular tradition of artist community meals. Building their respective experiences running performing venues and working with talent, Bragin and Bostwick sought to help shape the UAE art scene to center on the experience of the artist, even as much of the industry focuses on the audience. Through the community meals, they have sought to break through the superficiality of the standard visiting artist experience and build an intimate, community centered moment that forges new relationships and links artists to NYU Abu Dhabi, and the UAE as a whole. Sharing several anecdotes of interactions from the past five years, they offer a glimpse into the moments that make the community meals special. Despite the many challenges of the event, Bragin and Bostwick discuss its integral role in the Arts Center's mission and how to keep it a priority in the coming years.
  - Interview session with Malak Abdel-Ghaffar, Sara Pan Algarra, Alicja Borzyszkowska, Ian Hoyt (ElevatED), and Lauren Kata (44:44), 07 May 2020; ADRG023_014 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_014)
    Video-recorded session with NYUAD students Malak Abdel-Ghaffar, Sara Pan Algarra, Alicja Borzyszkowska, and Ian Hoyt, recorded on Thursday, May 7, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives.